{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The accused spy David Redding was hanged in what is now this state. Leaders from what is now this state negotiated with representatives of George Germain but failed to reach terms with Quebec governor Frederick Haldimand. This state celebrates Jonathan Stark's defeat of British forces before Saratoga on Bennington Battle Day. In 1791, this state became the 14th state to enter the Union, ending its Republic. For ten points, name this state for which Bernie Sanders has served as Senator.",
      "answer": "Vermont"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city was home to an early ecumenical [[ECK-yoo-MEN-ih-kull]] council which ruled that Gentiles were not required to keep Jewish laws. A religious leader in this city drove out moneylenders and kicked over tables in a temple he calls a \"house of prayer.\" This city is home to the Church of the Holy Sepulcher [[SEH-pull-kuhr]], which claims to be the location of Jesus's tomb. The location of the Last Supper, for ten points, what is this Israelite city where Jesus was crucified?",
      "answer": "Jerusalem"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's navy beat the Earl of Torrington and Ralph Delaval at the Battle of Beachy Head, preventing an invasion after his army won at Fleurus [[FLOOR-us]]. This man's attempts to install William von Furstenburg in Cologne [[ko-LOHN]] led to the creation of the League of Augsburg. This man gained Alsace and the Rhine River border with Germany at the Treaty of Ryswick [[RIZ-wik]]. This man revoked the Edict of Nantes and was served by Cardinal Mazarin. For ten points, name this Sun King of France.",
      "answer": "Louis XIV or Louis the Great"
    },
    {
      "question": "This body's internal structure was studied using the HP3 heat probe aboard the InSight lander in 2018. In 2022, the European/Russian-designed Rosalind Franklin is scheduled to land on this body. In 1877, Giovanni Schiaparelli [[skap-ah-REH-lee]] claimed to be able to see artificial canals on the surface of this body. Opportunity and Curiosity are two of the rovers which have landed on this body. The Perseverance rover searches for signs of ancient life on, for ten points, what fourth planet from the sun?",
      "answer": "Mars 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 2"
    },
    {
      "question": "This action shares roots with the Scandinavian tradition of Holmgang. Andrew Jackson is said to have lost his honor after violating the rules of one of these actions with Charles Dickinson. The shooting version of this action was an exhibition event at the 1906 and 1908 Olympics. Salvador Allende [[ah-YEN-day]] participated in this action with one of his future ambassadors, while Phillip Hamilton died in one of these actions in Weehawken, New Jersey. For ten points, name this honor challenge which occurred between Aaron Burr and Alexander Hamilton.",
      "answer": "Dueling"
    },
    {
      "question": "An \"Incident\" including the name of this month, perpetrated by the Cherry Blossom Society, attempted to abolish the liberal Taisho democracy in favor of the Showa Restoration. This month names a “Crisis” in which Pierre Trudeau was forced to enact the War Measures Act in Quebec. Alexander Kerensky’s provisional government was overthrown in a “Revolution” named for this month, leading to the Russian Civil War. For ten points, name this autumn month which, in 1917, included the rise of Vladimir Lenin and Soviet Russia.",
      "answer": "October"
    },
    {
      "question": "When analyzing this event, Slavoj Zizek [[SLAH-voh ZEE-zek]] applied Marxist and Lacanian analysis in the book Welcome to the Desert of the Real. This event inspired Borradori's [[boh-rah-DOH-rees]] dialogues with Habermas [[HAY-behr-mahs]] and Derrida [[DEH-rih-dah]], published under the title Philosophy in a Time of Terror. For ten points, name this terrorist attack, in which al-Qaeda agents destroyed two skyscrapers in New York.",
      "answer": "9/11 or September 11th"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the aftermath of one of these events, 231 Koreans were killed by mobs for allegedly causing it. The ruins of the Carmo Convent still stand after being damaged by one of these events in 1755, the first of these events to be scientifically analyzed. An early Chinese device for detecting these events featured dragons that dropped bronze balls into the mouths of toads. San Francisco's Chinatown was destroyed by one of these events in 1906 which also sparked devastating fires. For ten points, name these natural disasters in which the earth's surface shifts.",
      "answer": [
        "Earthquakes",
        "1923 Great Kanto earthquake",
        "1755 Great Lisbon earthquake",
        "1906 San Francisco earthquake 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 2"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this state, coordination between the Black farmers of Phillips County in the summer of 1919 led to white posses committing the Elaine Massacre. A governor of this state pressured David Hale into giving a 300 thousand dollar loan to family friend Jim McDougal in order to develop vacation homes in Whitewater. In 1957, Dwight D. Eisenhower force-integrated a high school in this state’s capital against the wishes of Governor Orval Faubus. For ten points, name this southern state with the cities of Hot Springs and Little Rock.",
      "answer": "Arkansas"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's wife commissioned the Godescalc [[GOH-deh-skahlk]] Evangelistary and brought the relics of Saints Gordianus and Epimachus [[EP-ih-MAH-kus]] to Kempten. Poets of the Veronese [[veh-roh-NEH-seh]] school praised the victory of this man's son Carloman over the Avars. Another of this man's sons named Louis blinded Bernard of Italy and issued the Ordinatio Imperii [[or-dih-NAH-tee-oh im-PEH-rih-ee]]. For ten points, name this Frankish Holy Roman Emperor, the grandson of the first Carolingian.",
      "answer": "Charlemagne or Charles the Great"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "James Moore's expedition in this state led to the Battle of Ayubale [[ai-YOO-bah- leh]]. Luis de Cáncer [[KAHN-sehr]] was martyred in this state when his mission from King Charles V led him into Tocobaga territory. After a war in the 1830s, about four thousand Seminoles and Black Seminoles were brought to Oklahoma from this state. In the 16th century, Tristán de Luna y Arellano [[ar-eh-YAHN-oh]] founded the Spanish colony of Ochuse [[oh-CHOO-say]] in this state's modern city of Pensacola. For ten points, name this southern U.S. state whose capital is Tallahassee.",
        "answer": "Florida"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "An archaeological park in St. Augustine, Florida, is touted as the 1513 landing site of Ponce de León, who was purportedly searching for this legendary spring said to provide a remedy to aging.",
        "answer": "Fountain of Youth"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one of these institutions, Frank “Big Black” Smith and Cleveland “Jomo” Davis led a notable 1971 uprising. The history of these facilities as an extension of slavery and segregation was chronicled by Michelle Alexander in The New Jim Crow. The number of these facilities grew in England due to unpopularity of the \"Bloody Code,\" under which individuals such as petty thieves could be given the death penalty. For ten points, name these facilities, whose overuse is referred to as \"mass incarceration.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Prisons",
          "jails",
          "penitentiarys"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "With Ruth Wilson Gilmore, this American activist founded Critical Resistance to help promote prison abolition. This feminist scholar was charged and later acquitted over her alleged involvement in the Soledad Brothers' courtroom kidnapping attempt.",
        "answer": "Angela Yvonne Davis"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was called the \"patient in a cast\" during the Aprillian government. The slogan \"Allag,\" or \"Change,\" was used by this country's PASOK party, which was brought down by the 1989 Koskotas [[kohs-KOH-tahs]] financial scandal. Students in this country cried \"Bread-Education-Liberty!\" during a 1973 strike targeting its Regime of the Colonels whose reign coincided with that of Constantine II. For ten points, name this country on the Aegean Sea, the site of the Athens Polytechnic uprising.",
        "answer": [
          "Greece or Hellenic Republic",
          "or Hellas"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Constantine II was the last king of Greece and the son of this ruler, who served from 1947 to 1964 and shared his name with a Biblical apostle.",
        "answer": "Paul of Greece 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 2"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During a crisis in this state, one mayor said that he was sick of \"lazy\" residents expecting a government \"handout.\" This state's governor falsely claimed that a power shortage in this state was due to renewable energy sources. In February 2021, four million residents of this state lost power due to Winter Storm Uri [[YOOR-ee]]. This state is the only one of the lower 48 states to have its own power grid. For ten points, name this state from which John Cornyn and Ted Cruz have served as U.S. senators.",
        "answer": "Texas"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This governor of Texas repeatedly refused to request FEMA or military aid during Winter Storm Uri, prompting speculation that Beto O'Rourke would challenge him in 2022.",
        "answer": "Greg Abbott"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During a battle for this city, P.O.W.s like the “Angels of Bataan” were rescued from the Santo Tomas internment camp. The first permanent Trans-Pacific trade route connected the port of Acapulco to this city and was used by the Spanish to exchange luxury goods and spices for New World silver. This city’s Epifanio de los Santos Avenue served as the hub of the People Power Revolution. For ten points, a battle in what capital city's bay led to the U.S. occupation of the Philippines?",
        "answer": "Manila"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This general’s recapture of Manila fulfilled the promise he made three years earlier in a speech stating, \"I came through, and I shall return\" following his retreat from the Philippines during World War Two.",
        "answer": "Douglas MacArthur"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Nations like Estonia and Persia sponsored a letter by this group presented to the League of Nations to gain further autonomy in two North American nations. This organization relinquished claims to the American Midwest in the Nanfan Treaty. This group, whose people resided in Longhouses, negotiated the Proclamation of 1763 to protect themselves from settler colonization past the Appalachians. Tribes like the Oneida and Mohawk made up, for ten points, which “Confederacy” of six nations who acted as allies of the British throughout the 18th century?",
        "answer": [
          "Iroquois Confederacy or Haudenosaunee",
          "Iroquois League",
          "Five Nations before \"Six\"",
          "Six Nations before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Iroquois Confederacy fought so-called “Mourning Wars” to gain this resource from rival tribes.",
        "answer": "Slaves 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 2"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In February 2021, this country's militarily-controlled Myawaddy TV falsely claimed that this country's de jure leader was released from custody. A 2021 coup d'état in this country resulted in Tatmadaw [[TAH-MUH-DOH]] leader Min Aung Hlaing [[MIN AHN LANG]] taking de facto power. This country's military was accused of carrying out an ethnic cleansing in Rakhine State of the Rohingya people. For ten points, name this Southeast Asian country where State Counsellor Aung San Suu Kyi [[CHEE]] was deposed.",
        "answer": [
          "Myanmar",
          "Burma"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the days after the coup in February 2021, thousands of protesters marched in the streets of this city, the largest in Myanmar.",
        "answer": "Yangon or Rangoon"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Ortoiroid [[or-TOY-roid]] people traveled to this island from Trinidad and Tobago. This island contained a similar culture to the Salidoid [[SAL-eh-doid]] culture called Hacienda Grande. Diego Salcedo was drowned on this island, which some believed took \"godliness\" from the Spaniards. This island, which locals called Boriken, was led by the cacique [[kah-SEE-keh]] Agüeybaná [[AH-gway-bah-NAH]], whose successor fought Ponce de León in the 1511 Taino Rebellion. For ten points, name this U.S. commonwealth in the Caribbean.",
        "answer": "Commonwealth of Puerto Rico"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Secretary of State unsuccessfully attempted to purchase Puerto Rico and Cuba from Spain but did manage to purchase Alaska from Russia in 1867.",
        "answer": "William Henry Seward"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Domestic Threats",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "White supremacist organization whose first grand wizard was Nathan Bedford Forrest",
          "answer": [
            "KKK",
            "Ku Klux Klan"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Nonprofit organization focusing on reproductive health which had one of its clinics attacked in 2015 by Robert Lewis Dear, Jr.",
          "answer": "Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Inc."
        },
        {
          "question": "Extremist who worked with Terry Nichols to bomb the Murrah building in Oklahoma City",
          "answer": "Timothy McVeigh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Texas city where federal agents raided the Mount Carmel Center occupied by followers of David Koresh.",
          "answer": "Waco"
        },
        {
          "question": "Church bombed in Birmingham in 1963",
          "answer": "16th Street Baptist Church"
        },
        {
          "question": "Deadly Idaho standoff that started after U.S. Marshals attempted to arrest Randy Weaver",
          "answer": "Ruby Ridge incident"
        },
        {
          "question": "Militant organization that organized the Days of Rage in response to the trial of the Chicago Seven",
          "answer": [
            "Weather Underground Organization",
            "the Weathermen"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Self-described far-left \"urban guerilla warfare group\" who kidnapped Patty Hearst in 1974",
          "answer": [
            "United Federated Forces of the Symbionese Liberation Army",
            "SLA 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 2"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Alexander the Great",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Greek kingdom he ruled from Pella before launching his conquests",
          "answer": "Macedonia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Father of Alexander who defeated Thebes at the Battle of Chaeronea",
          "answer": "Philip II of Macedon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of the Lyceum who tutored him in his youth",
          "answer": "Aristotle"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle in India where he defeated King Porus",
          "answer": "Battle of the Hydaspes River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Horse he rode for eighteen years who died at that battle",
          "answer": "Bucephalus ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term given to his successors who fought a series of wars that ended in 281 BC",
          "answer": "Diadochi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Persian satrap whom he had killed for betraying Darius III",
          "answer": [
            "Bessus",
            "Artaxerxes V"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City under the command of Batis which he was able to seize using tactics perfected at the Siege of Tyre",
          "answer": "Gaza 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 2"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Aboriginal Australians",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Large rock formation in the Northern Territory considered sacred to the local Aboriginal people",
          "answer": [
            "Uluru",
            "Ayers Rock"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Annual event held on May 26th in which the government apologizes to the Aboriginal community",
          "answer": [
            "National Sorry Day",
            "National Day of Healing"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Texas team for which Australian basketball player of Aboriginal heritage, Patty Mills, won a championship with Tim Duncan in 2014",
          "answer": [
            "San Antonio Spurs",
            "Spurs"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Kevin Rudd held this position when he offered an official apology to the Aboriginal people in 2008",
          "answer": "Prime Minister of the Commonwealth of Australia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Native inhabitants of a group of islands north of the Cape York Peninsula which include the Mabuiag and Merian people",
          "answer": "Torres Strait Islanders"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term given to thousands of Aboriginal children who were kidnapped and rehomed over a period of 70 years",
          "answer": "Stolen Generation"
        },
        {
          "question": "1997 report created by Ronald Wilson and Mick Dodson which investigated that group of children",
          "answer": [
            "Bringing Them Home",
            "Report of the National Inquiry into the Separation of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Children from Their Families"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Decade-long strategy launched in 2008 to reduce disparity between Aboriginals and the rest of Australia",
          "answer": "Closing the Gap 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 2"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "Mary Lucy Williams was nearly killed during a 1956 attack on this man's house. Two years later, Izola Curry nearly killed this man with a letter opener while he was signing copies of his book (*) Strive Toward Freedom. In a speech delivered at the Mason Temple, this man said, \"The issue is the refusal of Memphis to be fair and honest in its dealings with its public servants, who happen to be (*) sanitation workers.\" The next day, this man was shot at the Lorraine Motel. For ten points, name this Civil Rights activist who was assassinated in 1968."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Martin Luther King, Jr.",
        "MLK"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "One thinker from this country inspired a series of communes in the United States including Utopia, Ohio and Lake Zurich, Illinois. That thinker from this country proposed societies of 1,620 people, one male and one female from 810 personality types. In addition to that developer of the (*) \"phalanx\" system, this country was home to a philosopher who used the method of historical genealogy in books such as Madness and Civilization and (*) The Birth of the Clinic. For ten points, name this home country of Charles Fourier [[SHARL foo-RYEH]] and Michel Foucault [[mee-SHEL foo-KOH]]."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "France",
        "French Republic",
        "République Française",
        "Kingdom of France"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During a siege of this city, a two-month election was further worsened by the fact that guards urinated on voters from the Septizodium [[SEPT-ih-ZOH-dee-um]] roof. A tribune of this city, Cola di Rienzo, fought Stefano Colonna and was arrested by Charles IV. The (20 pts)",
        "Frangipani [[FRAHN-jee-PAH-nee]] and Pierleoni [[PEER-leh-OH- nee]] families feuded in this city in which Petrarch was crowned Poet Laureate. In 1279, (10 pts)",
        "Nicholas III moved the Papal seat from the Lateran Palace back to, for ten points, what Italian city's Vatican?"
      ],
      "answer": "Rome or Roma"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This composer was the alleged author of the posthumously published memoir Testimony. This composer's ballet The Limpid Stream was denounced by Platon Kerzhentsev [[plah-TOHN kehr-ZHEN-tsef]] for its depiction of peasant farmers. This composer was attacked for (*) formalism in the Pravda article \"Muddle Instead of Music.\" This composer's seventh symphony debuted during a Nazi (*) siege of its namesake city. For ten points, name this frequent target of Joseph Stalin, the Soviet composer of the Leningrad Symphony."
      ],
      "answer": "Dmitri Shostakovich 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 2"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country's Avellanada [[ah-veh-yah-NAH-dah]] laws allowed for European farmers to gain land. One leader of this country, Justo Jose de Urquiza [[uhr-KEE-zah]] fought Manuel Oribe [[oh-REE-beh]] and beat Juan Manuel de Rosas at (20 pts)",
        "Caseros [[kah-SEH-rohs]]. This nation was defended by the Army of the North, led by Martín Miguel de Güemes [[GWEH-mehs]], and the Army of the (10 pts)",
        "Andes was established in this country by native son, José de San Martín. For ten points, name this South American country with an oft-disputed Chilean border."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Republic of Argentina or Argentine Republic",
        "or República Argentina"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country contains the world's oldest known temple complex, whose name translates to \"Potbelly Hill.\" Ian Hodder currently has led the excavation of the Çatalhöyük [[cha-tal-HOH-yook]] temple in this country. The Dede [[DEH-DEH]] is a spiritual leader of this country's (20 pts)",
        "Alevi faith. This country is home to the headquarters of the Sufist Mevlevi Order, and this country's most important mosques include The Blue Mosque and the (10 pts)",
        "Hagia Sophia, originally a Byzantine Church. For ten points, name this country whose major Islamic sites are found in its city of Istanbul."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Republic of Turkey",
        "Türkiye Cumhuriyeti"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a religion-inspired war in this country, John Rantzau [[RAHNT-zow]] fought against Skipper Clement in the Count's Feud. This country lost to its neighbor in the Torstenson [[TOHR-sten-sun]] War and signed the treaty of (20 pts)",
        "Bromsebro [[BROOM- seb-roh]], resulting in its losing out on the Sound Dues. Christian IV of the Oldenburgs led this country in the Thirty Years' War and also founded (10 pts)",
        "Oslo during the time this country governed Norway. For ten points, name this Nordic country, mostly comprised of the Jutland peninsula."
      ],
      "answer": "Kingdom of Denmark"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "A work by this man begins \"Universal empire is the prerogative of a writer\" and also states that a continent will \"startle at the unhallowed foot of an invader\" even when whispering a \"delusion\" like \"Satan to Eve.\" (*) \"Tyranny, like hell, is not easily conquered,\" according to this man, who also writes, \"These are the times that try men's souls.\" In addition to The American Crisis, this man wrote a best seller and donated the proceeds to the (*) American Patriots. For ten points, name this British- American author of Common Sense."
      ],
      "answer": "Thomas Paine 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 2"
    }
  ]
}